Finding Aid for the ANTA West records, 1958-1977 LSC.1965
UCLA Library Special Collections
ANTA West records
1958-1977
UCLA Library Special Collections
ANTA West (Organization)
LSC.1965
6.75 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
ANTA West was a non profit corporation organized in the state of California, in September 1957, to stimulate public interest in the performing arts and to foster and support live theatrical activity. The collection consists of files related to their activities and includes meeting minutes, committee reports, correspondence, financial records, and publications.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Box 15 is restricted from access.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Wintersole.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9969666813606533
Historiography
ANTA West (American National Theater and Academy West) was originally chartered as the Greater Los Angeles Chapter of the American National Theatre and Academy, Inc. In the early years, the organization was also known as the ANTA Southern California Chapter and/or the ANTA Los Angeles-Southern California Chapter. In May 1957, John Angelo and David Bond, along with a group of about one-hundred West Coast participants, met with ANTA National Executive Director Willard Swire, and it was decided that a Los Angeles ANTA chapter would be formed. Angelo and Bond were selected as co-chairs of a temporary action committee to work with ANTA Regional Director Wray Davis. Later that month, the first organizational meeting was held at the Huntington Hartford Theater with more than 250 people in attendance. Among the panelists at the first meeting were David Bond, Wray Davis, Jack Morrison (UCLA drama department), Kent Smith, and Grayce Smith. A major outcome of the meeting was a decision that a California non-profit corporation be formed; Grayce Smith, a prominent theatrical attorney, was to prepare the incorporation papers. A temporary board of directors was appointed to draw up a constitution and by-laws for the chapter. Seventy-five members supported the founding of the local Southern California ANTA chapter.
In July 1957, a second meeting was held to update members with progress, aims and requirements. By September 1957, approval was secured for the non-profit corporation and proposed constitution and by-laws were submitted to the national ANTA for consideration. A nominating committee was chosen and a new board was elected by popular vote: Helen Ainsworth, Jon Angelo, David Bond, Gilmor Brown, Dr. James Butler, Wray Davis, Nico Lek de Tachinville, Charles Lane, Kate Drain Lawson, Jack Morrison, Maddie Norman, Dr. David Sievers, Clarence Straight, Walter Wanger, and Harry Zevin. The first board of directors met in December and elected officers to serve for 1958: David Bond, president; James Butler and Maddie Norman, vice president; Harry Zevin, secretary; and Nico Lek de Tachinville, treasurer. An executive committee was elected to be the operating body of the chapter. The greater Los Angeles chapter of ANTA was now charted, incorporated and functioning. In 1974 the organization renamed itself ANTA West.
Throughout the years, their mandate, to stimulate public interest in the performing arts and to foster and support theatrical activities, remained constant. Chief among their aims and objectives were the support and production of quality theater events locally and nationally, the encouragement and assistance to accredited training in the performing arts in colleges and universities, and facilitating training workshop opportunities for theater professionals. Their many activities over the years included: the publication of a local newsletter to disseminate information about theatrical activities and opportunities in the Southern California area, the radio broadcast of ANTA Newsletter-of-the-Air on KUSC to report on the current theater scene to the community, partnering for the productions of "Our Town" and "I do, I do", the sponsorship of the American College Theater Festival, workshops and other educational opportunities, the support for Children's theater festivals and other local, state, county and regional activities, and the innovative operation show bus program, which provided tickets and bus service to students to introduce them to the theater. Over the years, leadership included: David Bond, Wray Davis, Ludwig Gerber, Arthur O'Connell, Milton Krims, Francis Lederer, Leon Ames, John Houseman, Dr. Jacob Lichstein, Albert Salmi, Ruth Burch, John Forsythe, Jack Morrison, Elza Schallert, Grayce M. Smith, Ezra Stone, and Harry Zevin, among others. ANTANS, an auxiliary group of ANTA West, was often responsible for fundraising for the organization.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of files related to the activities of ANTA West (American National Theatre and Academy West), a non-profit corporation organized in California in 1957 to encourage public interest in the performing arts and to foster and support live theatrical activity. Included are meeting minutes for the Executive Committee, Board of Directors, and other committees, committee reports, correspondence, financial records such as budgets and expenses for projects, programs for various productions, and publications such as the ANTA newsletter. In addition there is a small amount material related to the ANTANS in and among some of the files. Many of the envelopes found in the collection are addressed to William Wintersole, who served in a number of capacities within the organization. It should be noted that ANTA West is often noted as ANTA on file folders, not to be confused with ANTA (American National Theatre and Academy), the national level organization. Notably absent from the records are materials documenting the closing of ANTA West.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by file titles.
Theater -- California -- History -- Archives.; ANTA West (Organization)--Archives.
- Actors committee finances, (1973) (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Agendas and minutes, (1973-1976) (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Aims and Objectives, (1974) (Box 2, Folder 12)
- ANTA accountance prepared reports, (1972-1973) (Box 12, Folder 4)
- ANTA album, (1972) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- ANTA awards ball and dinner (Rosalind Russell), (1974) (Box 8, Folder 10)
- ANTA benefit tickets, receipts and production stills, (1973) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- ANTA budget, (1974-1975) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- ANTA financial statements (Folder 1 of 2), (1964-1968, 1970-1971) (Box 11, Folder 3)
- ANTA financial statements (Folder 2 of 2), (1964-1968, 1970-1971) (Box 11, Folder 4)
- ANTA I do I do, (1973) (Box 12, Folder 3)
- ANTA insurance, (1972) (Box 11, Folder 2)
- ANTA lease - Ross, (1975) (Box 7, Folder 6)
- ANTA National Artists Award - Rosalind Russell souvenir program and Helen Hayes promotional letter, (1976) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- ANTA newsletter, (1970) (Box 8, Folder 9)
- ANTA newsletter expense, (1973) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- ANTA newsletters, (1974-1975) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- ANTA newsletters, (1974) (Box 7, Folder 13)
- ANTA paid bills, (1971) (Box 12, Folder 2)
- ANTA payroll returns and wage and tax statements, (1971-1972) (Box 15)
  General note
  RESTRICTED ACCESS. These materials are restricted due to privacy information and require advanced notice for use.
- ANTA Players Unit activities and Tuesday nighters, (1973) (Box 7, Folder 2)
- ANTA playreading report, (1973) (Box 8, Folder 7)
- ANTA playwrights' letters, (1973-1974) (Box 8, Folder 6)
- ANTA southern California chapter newsletter, (1973) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ANTA Southern California Chapter newsletters, (1973) (Box 4, Folder 6)
- ANTA treasury correspondence, (1973) (Box 8, Folder 3)
- ANTA volunteer project forms and information, (1976) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- ANTA West activities, (1974-1976) (Box 5)
  Meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, financial records, newsletters and publicity.
- ANTA West activities, (1973-1974) (Box 6)
  Meeting minutes, correspondence, financial records, newsletters and publicity.
- ANTA West activities, (1960-1972) (Box 13)
  Meeting minutes, committee reports, correspondence, seventh annual national assembly, ANTANs newsletters, San Diego productions and election material (1970-1971).
- ANTA West activities, (1972-1977) (Box 14)
  Board activities, committee reports, correspondence, financial records, Los Angeles Free Shakespeare Festival, Theatre Complex proposal, meeting minutes and publicity.
- ANTA West voucher book (blank), (no date) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- ANTA-LA Newsletters, (1961-1962) (Box 4, Folder 5)
- ANTANS Board list, (1972) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- ANTA's history, (no date) (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Bicentennial, (1974) (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Board and committees, (1973) (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Board meeting minutes, (1975) (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Board meeting minutes, committee reports, election material and financial information, (1976) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Board meeting minutes, committee reports, membership information and correspondence, (1977) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Board minutes, executive committee minutes, financial information and newsletters, (1960s) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, (1962, 1969) (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Board of Directors minutes, (1971) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Box office and group sales forms, (ca. 1970) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Box office statements, expenses, invoices and receipts, (1975) (Box 8, Folder 15)
  From envelope labeled Reports, Memos, Time Slips.
- Brochure 76, (1960) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  With Los Angeles Theatre Club memorandum, odds and ends.
- Budgets, (1973-1974) (Box 2, Folder 13)
- By-laws, (no date) (Box 2, Folder 15)
- By-laws, (no date) (Box 12, Folder 1)
- By-laws expense, (1974) (Box 2, Folder 10)
- California Arts Commission, (1974) (Box 8, Folder 14)
  Communication arts.
- Checkbook, (1972) (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Chorus line contracts, (1976) (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Committee activity, reports, budgets, minutes and election information, (1970s) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, (1973) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, (1972) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Dance and musical theatre, (1973-1974) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Dancers: A Tragedy in Three Acts by Brendan Ward, (c. 1975) (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Executive secretary, (1974) (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Ezra Stone itinerary, (1976) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Financial reports, by-laws and expenses, (1975) (Box 4, Folder 1)
- General membership meeting, (1973) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Helen Hayes ad book album orders, (1976) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Housing expense, (1973-1974) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Lease - Pilgrimage, (1967) (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Letter to Wintersole, (1977) (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Lunts' dinner and show, (1972-1973) (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Mailing lists, (1976) (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Meeting minutes, (1958-1974) (Box 9)
  Meeting minutes, letters, project reports and other documents. Some documents related to theater projects.
- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, Old Bylaws, (1976-1977) (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Meeting minutes, reports, promissory notes and ANTA West Loyola Marymount University proposal, (1975-1976) (Box 10)
- Membership, (1973) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Membership, (1974) (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Membership meeting minutes, (1972) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Minutes, (1970) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Minutes, (1974) (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Minutes of ANTA Board of Directors' Meetings, (1971-1973) (Box 4)
- Negatives, (1974) (Box 7, Folder 20)
  Some labeled Dance Spectrum 74
- Newsletter expense, (1974) (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Newsletter of the Air expense, (1974) (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Nominating committee, (1974) (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Nominating committee expense, (1974) (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Phone call expense vouchers, (1975) (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Playbills, (1965) (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Players unit expense, (1974) (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Playwrights' expense, (1974) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Post office info bulk mail, (1972) (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Programs and projects, (1973) (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Programs and projects expense, (1974) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Programs and souvenir programs, (1958-1972) (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Public information relations expense, (1973) (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Roz Russell party '74, (1973) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Committee meeting minutes, handwritten notes, org chart.
- Russell ad book orders, (1976) (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Russell ball, (1974) (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Sea Horse (The) - stage plan, (no date) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Secretary services expense, (1973) (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Six month accounting, (1972-1973) (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Six month accounting, (1973) (Box 12, Folder 6)
- South Pacific program, (1958) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Telephone expense, (1973) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Theatre for Your City booklet, (no date) (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Treasury, (1974) (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Treasury receipts, (1973) (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Voucher and Petty Cash Records, receipts, statements, (1975) (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Workshop expense, (1973) (Box 2, Folder 14)